Guide to the George Lincoln Hendrickson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Lincoln Hendrickson papers
1886-1962
MS 1272
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
(5 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings, notes, minutes, printed material, memorabilia, and photographs, 1886-1962, documenting the personal and professional life of George Lincoln Hendrickson, a classicist, philologist, professor of Latin at several institutions, and chairman of Yale's Department of Classics. The papers include correspondence, writings, and research materials concerning classical philology, Latin and Latin literature. Correspondents include prominent European and American philologists, classicists and educators such as Franz Cumont, Basil L. Gildersleeve, and Minton Warren. Departmental minutes and correspondence document Hendrickson's term as chairman of Yale's Department of Classics, 1912-1919 and 1925-1933. Correspondence with Mikhail I. Rostovtsev and Charles C. Torrey concerning the excavations at Dura Europos, and classical excavation at Yale and other institutions is included.
Hendrickson, G. L. (George Lincoln), 1865-1963
Related Materials
For further materials by and about Hendrickson, readers should consult the C. - E. A. Winslow Papers, MS Group No. 749; and Faculty of Arts and Sciences: Classics, YRG 14-H.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George Lincoln Hendrickson, 1963.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Departmental Papers, 1896-1953. II. Correspondence, 1886-1962. III. Writings and Notes, 1891-1951. IV. Memorabilia and Photographs, 1894-1959.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of correspondence, writings, notes, minutes, printed material, memorabilia, and photographs, 1886-1962, documenting the professional and personal life of George Lincoln Hendrickson, a classicist, philologist, professor of Latin at several institutions, and chairman of Yale's Department of Classics.
The papers include correspondence, writings, and research materials concerning classical philology, Latin, and Latin literature. Correspondents include prominent European and American philologists, classicists, and educators such as Franz Cumont, Basil L. Gildersleeve, and Minton Warren.
Departmental minutes and correspondence document Hendrickson's terms as chairman of the Department of Classics at Yale, 1912-1919 and 1925-1933. Correspondence with Mikhail I. Rostovtzeff and Charles C. Torrey concerns the excavations at Dura-Europos; other correspondence concerns classical education at Yale and other institutions.
Additional materials include personal correspondence and memorabilia, and writings and printed matter concerning the Phi Beta Kappa Society at Yale.
The George L. Hendrickson Papers are arranged in four series:
I. DEPARTMENTAL PAPERS, 1896-1953 II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1886-1962 III. WRITINGS AND NOTES, 1891-1951 IV. MEMORABILIA AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1894-1959
Series I, DEPARTMENTAL PAPERS, consists primarily of records from Hendrickson's terms as head of the Yale Classics Department. The papers include correspondence relating to faculty appointments and departmental budgets; correspondence concerning Dura-Europos; correspondence with other universities regarding their classics departments and the importance attached to research; papers concerning the publication of the series,Yale Classical Studies. Also included is a volume of minutes of faculty meetings.
Series II, CORRESPONDENCE, contains letters from colleagues, students, friends, and family. The early correspondents, in particular, include many prominent scholars, writing in English, German, French and Italian.
Series III, WRITINGS AND NOTES, is the largest series, and it documents many of Hendrickson's scholarly research projects, as well as some of his classroom work and personal interests. The major topics are classical philology and text criticism; Latin, including the etymology of the work "syphilis"; Latin literature, especially satire; and the New Testament Gospels. Materials in this series include manuscripts, typescripts, and reprints of articles, lectures, occasional papers, book reviews, and letters to the editor, research materials, and notes.
Series IV, MEMORABILIA AND PHOTOGRAPHS, contains writings of students and colleagues; memorabilia, including Latin statements and Latin Phi Beta Kappa Society speeches by Hendrickson; printed matter, including a bibliography of his writings; and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
GEORGE LINCOLN HENDRICKSON, 1865-1963
George Lincoln Hendrickson was born on May 15, 1865, in Winchester, Illinois. He was a classicist, philologist, and educator. He died on December 18, 1963, at the age of ninety-eight.
Hendrickson attended Johns Hopkins University (B.A. 1887) and studied at Bonn and Berlin. He was a professor of classics, specializing in Latin, at several institutions. His longest service was at Yale University, as professor (1908-1933), chairman of the Department of Classics (1912-1919, 1925-1933), lecturer (1933-1938), and professor emeritus (1933-1963). Hendrickson married Marion Vaux in 1897.
Chronological History
1865 born May 15, Winchester, Illinois, son of Rev. William A. and Ada M.(French) Hendrickson
1887 received Bachelor of Arts degree from Johns Hopkins University
1888-1889 studied at Bonn and Berlin, Germany
1889-1891, 1889-1896, 1897-1907 professor of Latin, Colorado College, University of Wisconsin, University of Chicago
1897 married Marion Vaux
1908-1909 professor of Latin language and literature, Yale University
1909-1912 Lampson Professor of Latin language and literature, Yale University
1912-1933 Lampson Professor of Latin and Greek literature, Yale University
1912-1919, 1925-1933 chairman, Department of Classics, Yale University
1913-1914, 1919-1920 Acting director, director, American School of Classical Studies in Rome
1921-1922 Sather Professor of classical literature, University of California
1931-1932 lecturer in classical literature, Harvard University
1933-1963 professor emeritus, Yale University
1933-1938 lecturer in classics, Yale University
1933-1948, 1948-1963 fellow, associate fellow of Branford College, Yale University
1936 president, American Philological Association
1963 died December 18
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Classical education; Latin literature; Educators; Cumont, Franz, 1868-1947; Gildersleeve, Basil L. (Basil Lanneau), 1831-1924; Hendrickson, G. L. (George Lincoln), 1865-1963; Rostovtzeff, Michael Ivanovitch, 1870-1952; Torrey, Charles Cutler, 1863-1956; Warren, Minton, 1850-1907; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Classics
- Departmental Papers, 1896-1953; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged by record type, in alphabetical order. Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1911-1914, 1918-1919, 1925-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [Faculty Club?] papers, 1914-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1896-1912 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1886-1962; Series II
  This series is arranged chronologically. Two folders of Christmas cards, also arranged chronologically, have been separated and placed at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1886-1914, 1920-1961 March (Box 2, Folder 11-17)
  - Correspondence, 1961 April-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Christmas cards, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
- Writings and Notes, 1891-1951; Series III
  This series is arranged chronologically. Undated materials have been grouped roughly by topic.
  - 1891-1899 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - 1920-1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 25-27)
  - Undated (Box 4, Folder 28-34)
- Memorabilia and Photographs, 1894-1959; Series IV
  This series is organized by type of material. Each folder is arranged chronologically.
  - Writings of others, 1896, 1943, 1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Society, Yale College: programs, Latin speeches by GLH, 1907, 1915-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Congratulatory statements in Latin, mostly by GLH, 1930-1956, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    General note
    See also: box 6
  - Printed matter, 1894-1905, 1922-1936, 1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Photographs, calling cards, autographs, postcards, Undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Congratulatory statements in Latin, mostly by GLH, 1936-1937, undated (Box 6)
    Folio
  - Diplomas, certificates, honorary degrees, 1887-1933 (Box 6)